Now we will further continue our same example and see how we can filter columns, filter rows, as well as
order record set with multiple columns. Let's start with a very simple example.
Here, we have SELECT * FROM sakila.actor WHERE first_name = ‘Nick'. As we have seen, we are going to get four
columns because there is * and three rows because we have first_name = ‘Nick'. Let's execute it and, as expected,
we can see now four columns and three rows. Let's assume that we don't need last_update column. Well remove that.
Now we will not use *, instead of that we'll specify actor_id, first_name, and last_name. While we do that, we'll
also add one more twist. Currently, we are getting our data, which is this spot, actor_id ascending.
Let's change the sequence and we want now data, which is ‘ORDER BY actor_id DESC'. What it means is that we want
our very first record to be 166 and very last record to be 2. We can easily do that if we specify only three columns
in a SELECT statement and additionally we provide ‘ORDER BY actor_id (sequences) DESC'.
Let's select this and execute. You can see now we are getting 166 as the top record and 2 as bottom record.
Currently our result is ORDER BY only one column, which is actor_id. Let's make it more complicated.
I'll change the WHERE condition and I'm retrieving, once again, actor_id &gt; 100. Here we have ORDER BY first_name,
which is ascending, and last_name, which is descending. Additionally, we have three columns, which is actor_id,
first_name, and last_name. What it means is that we have all the elements which we have learned together in this
single query. We are filtering by columns; additionally, we are filtering by rows. Also, we are ordering this
complete resultset by multiple columns, which is first_name and last_name. Let's execute this and now we have
resultset. We can clearly see that every single record in first column actor_id is over 100.
Additionally, let's pay attention to the first name. You can see that first_name ‘ADAM' is on the top and
‘WILLIAM' is on the bottom. What it means is that first_name is order ascending alphabetically.
However, there is also last_name, which is order descending. What it means is that after the first_name column
is order alphabetically ascending, MySQL will pay attention to last_name column. Let's see an example.
Look at these two lines. We have first_name ‘GORDON' and last_name is ‘NOLTE' and ‘JACKMAN'.
You can see last_name is now order descending because N comes first and J is now coming later on.
Here is the example where we have our cell. If you think of alphabets, you can see the B should come first; however,
we have ordered last_name descending. What it means is that now D is coming first and later, C and B.
So, MySQL has first order complete data as per first_name ascending and later order complete resultset by
last_name descending. Let's see a tricky concept next where we retrieve empty resultset.