Now we will see a demonstration of how we use Arithmetic Expressions, as well as column aliases.
By default, MySQL gives column in the resultset the same name as the column in a base table; however, for
business needs, we can specify a different name known as column alias. If a column is based on calculated values,
by default the name of the column is the complete expression. This automatically assigned expression is usually
very difficult to read, as well as write. It's always a good idea to assign the column alias to a column,
which either has a calculated value or very complicated name. We will see that in a demonstration later this clip.
MySQL values any arithmetic expression from left to right. The order of precedence is as follows: Multiplication,
Division, Integer Division, Modulo, Addition, and Subtraction. If you have multiplication and addition in the
same expression, MySQL will first perform multiplication and later, addition. When we are reading from left
to right, we forget the importance of order of precedence. If you want to avoid confusion, it's always a good
idea to use parentheses. Parentheses avoids confusion, as well as gives you expected results.
Arithmetic expressions involving multiplication, division, addition, and subtraction are very common.
Modulo or remainder or integer division are not commonly used arithmetic expressions.
You will see in the next demo, how we can use these various arithmetic expressions in MySQL queries.