Now let's understand the concept of aliases with example. Let's first retrieve a few columns from
sakila.rental table. Select the statement and click on Execute. You can see we have retrieved three columns --
rental_date, inventory_id, and return_date. Due to any reason, if you do not like these column names, we can just
change them. For changing column names, we just have to alias them. For example, in this SELECT statement,
rental_date is original column name. We can just say ‘rental_date AS RentalDate' in the CamelCase and now,
this is our alias. Similarly for inventory_id, we are also aliasing it as FilmListID. For return_date, the alias
is ReturnDate in CamelCase. Let's select this statement and execute it. You can see in the resultset that
original column names are now replaced with column aliases. However, the data which is being displayed right
after the header title, it's the same and there is no difference at all. So in other words, aliases is just
another name for any of the columns. Well there is not much of the importance of alias at this point of time;
however, alias becomes very very important when we are dealing with arithmetic expressions.
For example, ‘FROM sakila.film' table, we are retrieving three different columns and two of them have arithmetic
operations. Let's select the statement and execute it. You can see the column names are very wide.
The most easy way to fix this problem is to just alias a column. Let's see that now. You can see in this example,
I have aliased ‘replacement cost -- rental_rate AS CostDiff', length/60 is now alias ‘AS TimeinHour'.
Let's execute this statement and you can see that column width is much lesser and it's very easy to read.
You can see in this SELECT statement we have used various different arithmetic operators.
For example, we have +, *, and -; however, to make this more interesting, I have used parentheses that are
in different places. Select this entire statement and now click on Execute. You can see that arithmetic
operation on original column changes the complete meaning of the column. Now let's see one more example.
Let's select this particular statement and click on Execute. Here, you can see each column has a different value.
You can see the original column, replacement_cost, is now aliased with ReplacementCost in CamelCase.
Right after that, it is divided by 5. Our result will be decimal. However, if you don't want decimal result,
we can just use the word DIV, it will give us integer results. We can also find very quickly, modulo or remainder
of any value. For example, here we have value 20.99. When it is divided by 5, we are getting the value as 4.198.
When we use the DIV function, it will only give us integer part of this decimal value. In this case, it's a 4;
in this case, it's 2; in this case, it's 3. Here, there is a 12.99. When we divide that with 5, our remainder is 2.99.
Now you can see how various arithmetic operations come together with the regular SELECT statement and start
building intelligent data.