Here, we are back in MySQL Workbench and we will see a demonstration related to integer, string, and
date functions. If you see the list of all the functions in MySQL, the list is extremely large.
It's just impossible to cover each and every function and explain them in a single clause; however,
we'll see a few of the important functions in this demonstration. Once you know how to use one function in
SELECT statement, you can go and use any other function in SELECT statement as easily.
We'll very first see how integer works. Here is the statement where I'm retrieving data from payments table.
Let's first select the data and later we will understand what each of these functions do.
Select the statement and click on Execute. Now we can see we have five different columns displayed in our resultset.
The very first column is amount. You can see amount is directly retrieved as it is from payment table.
We have not modified or applied any function over it. The second column over here is using round function.
Round function rounds up or rounds down any of the decimal value to nearest integer. You can see 2.99 is
converted to 3 and .99 is converted to 1. If you scroll down, you will see the similar examples over here.
In the third column, once again we have used round function; however, this time we are specifying second parameter
over here. Second parameter we have passed as 1. What it means is that when you round up or round down,
at that time display information to first decimal. For example, over here you can see now 1 is 1.0.
To see them further into action, let's take one more example where we will not use any FROM clause,
but right of it take integer will do and try to apply round over it. Let's write SELECT ROUND and function.
Now let's pass here value 4.5 and let's execute it. You can see it's now rounded up to value 5.
If you pass 4.99, it would still round up to 5; however, if you pass 4.49, it will round it down to the 4.
Let's go back to our statement and execute it again. Now we'll do one function to look at it.
FLOOR rounds down any of the value to the nearest lowest integer, whereas CEILING rounds up any value to nearest
high integer. Let's see an example over here. Here, we have a value of 2.99. Then we applied function FLOOR over here.
It has rounded it down to 2 and when we apply CEILING function over here, it is rounded up to the 3.
Though they look very simple, these are very important functions and comes very handy when we are dealing
with numbers.