In this demo, we will see how we can do some of the very common string operations
with string functions. For example, joining two string and making it a single string. One of the most common tasks
every developer faces is to concat two strings. For example, if you have first_name and last_name, if you want
to display a full name, you just have to concat two strings. MySQL is in BUILD function, which we can use to just
concat string. For example, here we have concat function. We can pass multiple parameters over here.
I will pass three parameters. First is first_name ‘ ‘ and last_name. Now, let's execute this one.
Select the statement and click on Execute. I have aliased the column ‘AS FullName'. Under the FullName column,
you can see now first name and last name are displayed together with the space between them.
You can see how easy MySQL makes it to join two or more strings. If your need is to just display initial of the person,
you can do that using MySQL as well. Here is our second example where I'll use function code LEFT.
LEFT takes two parameters, first is a string and second one is how many characters you want to select from
the left side. Here I'm applying LEFT function on the first_name, as well as on the last_name, and both the times
I'm just selecting one character. When we run this complete SELECT statement, you can see that, along with the
FullName, now we are able to see the initials. Currently, initials has a space between them because I have left
space over here. If you remove this space and comma and execute it again, you can see that now initial does not
have a space between them. Similarly there is a function called RIGHT, which will just select the right-most rows.
Currently, we are selecting only one character. Let's make it two for first_name and last_name.
Now let's execute it one more time. You can see this time that we are getting first two characters, first_name
and last_name. For example, we are selecting PE from PENELOPE and GU for GUINESS. Similar thing is for NICK,
we are selecting NI and for WAHLBERG, we are taking WA. As we know, we are selecting only two rows from first initial
and last initial, the string which is built for initial has a fixed length. However, in case of the ordering of
first_name and last_name, we really do not know what is the length of this string. We can use function LENGTH and
can figure it out, LENGTH of our first_name and last_name together. For example, here I'm concatenating
first_name and last_name and applying LENGTH function over it. Let's execute this complete statement and here it is.
For example, NICK WAHLBERG has 13 characters and JENNIFER DAVIS has now 14 characters.
One of the functions is REVERSE. What it will do is that it will take the complete string and display as in
the REVERSE order. We can use this function to figure it out while in (inaudible). Let's execute this one.
Now in the resultset, the first column is FullName, which is the origin of FullName. You can see NICK WAHLBERG
is over, but when we see the reverse FullName, it is now spelled backwards. For example, last character's G is
the first character over here and second to last character, which is R, is now second character over here.
Let's examine our REPLACE function. For example, in JENNIFER DAVIS, we have S as the last character.
When we see the replaced example, we can find DAVI and $ because our S is now replaced with $.
Similar thing is also there with GRACE MOSTEL. In this case, S is once again replaced with $.
You can use this REVERSE and REPLACE function and can do a lot of different things. Next, we will see function
related to date and time.