Now we will see some of the functions related to DATE.
One of the most used function is DATE_FORMAT function. Every country and every geographic region has their
own format. When we are dealing with an application which is using a multiple country, we are to carefully pay
attention to the date and time. In our daily routine and in our application, we need a different part of the date.
Sometimes we need to know date part and sometimes we just need time part. Let's see some of the date and time
functions right now. Let's see this very first script. Select the statement and click on Execute and here,
you can see the date is first and the month is in the middle. Also, one of the other differences between these
two columns is how year is spelled. If you look at the last column, it's also very differently formatted.
Even the date and time are the same, the way it is displayed are different. In my circle, we have a different
marks for date and time. For example, when we have m, d, and y in the smaller letters, they're each mapped
to month, day, and two digit year. If we just capitalize Y, it means now four digit year.
Similar way, if you want your month to represent with three-character string, you can just use small b.
Capital T stands for the time and F stands for precision of the time. If you search for function date-format
in my SQL documentation, you can find details of each and every mask available for DATE_FORMAT.
For example, A stands for abbreviated weekday name, whereas small h stands for hour. Capital H stands for now Hour
as well, but in 24 hour system. If you want day of the week, you can just use small w and if you want weekday name,
you can just use capital W and if you go further up in the MySQL documentation, the 12th section is dedicated to
Functions and Operators and over here, you can find out various numeric functions and operators, as well as
string functions. Here is the entire list of string functions and operators, which you can practice out each one
at a time. Similar way, here is the list of string functions. Let's go to next script. Now we can see that we can
change this mask and build the date and time format as we want. Let's go to next script.
Here is the DATE_FORMAT. It's quite possible that we are not familiar with each country or each zones.
At that time, we can use a very interesting function, which is GET_FORMAT. What GET_FORMAT does is that instead
of specifically mask, it will automatically get the format based on your date and time from the zone which
you specify. For example, let's execute this. Select the statement and click on Execute.
Now we have four columns and you can see on the very first column, if you carefully pay attention to each of these
columns, you can notice that they have a same value. The reason is very simple, that GET_FORMAT when we use with
the DATETIME for EUR, ISO or USA, it gives us the same time format. Now I replace DATETIME with TIME and let's
execute the script again. When you execute the script again, now we can clearly see that all the column has a
different information. You can see over here the column #1 and last has pretty much the same information;
however, date and month are swapped. In Europe, the date is always first and in USA, month is always first and
in ISO format, year in the four digit month and date. Let's first execute this script and later we will
understand the output. In our result time, we have five columns. First, is rental_date, which is the original
date time and other four columns. The date is 2005-05-24, it was the third week of the day, and it was in the
second quarter, as month is May. This particular month was 21st week of the year. Well, MySQL has a default
function where it will give you day of the week, quarter of the year, week of the year, and name of the month.
You can just use any of these functions and pass your DATETIME as one of the parameters, it will give you the output,
which you are expecting. With this, we end our clip, but you can notice that how easy it is to use various
function in a SELECT statement and can get desired output.