Now in this demonstration, we will understand how DISTINCT keyword impacts query resultset.
Before we execute query, let's look at the Output Window. Go over here in MySQL Workbench and click it here to
display Output Window. We'll first execute SELECT first_name FROM sakila.actor. Select the statement and click
on Execute. You can see the resultset over here, as well as can notice there are 200 rows returned from this query.
Now we will execute second query. The only difference between first query and second query is DISTINCT keyword.
We have additionally added DISTINCT keyword because now we want unique first_name from sakila.actor.
Let's execute this one and this time, you can notice that we only receive 130 rows. What it means is that there
were 70 records, which were duplicate. Now duplicate records are eliminated and we can only see DISTINCT resultsets.
Let's run it again for last_name. Select last_name from sakila.actor and click on Execute.
From resultset, you can clearly see that ALLEN last_name is there multiple times, as well as BERRY.
Now we will learn another SELECT statement where we have DISTINCT keyword right before the last_name.
Select the query and click on Execute. Now ALLEN is only displayed once, so is BERRY. If you look at the
Output Window, we can see that when we selected last_name from sakila.actor, at that time MySQL returned 200 rows.
However, as soon as we added DISTINCT keyword, it has returned us only 123 rows. We can use DISTINCT with multiple
columns, as well as with star. The purpose of the DISTINCT is to return unique rows based on the column used
in a SELECT statement.