Developers use SELECT statement for various purposes. Here is a list of few of the examples where we use
SELECT statement: Retrieve static value, retrieve all the data from table, retrieve all the data ordered
by single column, retrieve selected columns from table, retrieve data with filter condition, retrieve the data
with filter condition and ordered by multiple columns, retrieve empty resultset.
In this module, we will see examples of this, as well as a few real-world scenarios.
Let's start with understanding basic syntax of SELECT statement.
A basic SELECT statement has five clauses. SELECT clause: It describes the column in resultset.
FROM clause: Names the base table from which the query retrieves data. We can also use views here, but that's
advanced concept. WHERE clause: It specifies the condition that must be met for any row to be retrieved in
resultset. ORDER BY clause: It specifies how to sort the rows in resultset. We can have one column or multiple
columns, by which we can order resultset. LIMIT clause: It specifies the number of the rows to return.
Sometimes tables are very huge and it's important that we retrieve only a limited number of the rows for
various reasons. In Basic Syntax of SELECT statement, we have not included all the clauses in this Basic Syntax of
SELECT statement. For example, HAVING clause: HAVING clause filters data based on aggregate functions.
In our advanced course, we will be talking about aggregate function. At the same time we will explore HAVING clause
and also understand difference between WHERE clause and HAVING clause. Now let's see SELECT statement in action.