Here we are in MySQL Workbench in SQL Query Editor. Let's see some of the examples how WHERE clause works with
comparison operators. First, we will see how equal operator works with integer and string.
We will be using sakila.actor table for this demonstration. Let's not select the WHERE clause and select
SELECT column name FROM sakila.actor. Click on Execute. We can see that it has returned us entire table.
Let's also enable Output Window. In Output Window, we can see it has returned us 200 rows.
Now, let's execute this entire query with WHERE condition where ‘actor_id = 100'. Select this row and click
on Execute. You can see in Output Window it has retrieved only one row and the row is ‘actor_id = 100'.
Instead of selecting entire table, we should be passing WHERE condition and select the row, which is needed.
Here, we are comparing column name with string operator. As mentioned earlier, for integer you do not need a
single code around it; however, for string, you need a single code around your parameter.
Now let's select this query and execute it. You can see in result pane it has retrieved us three rows and
similar results are also reflected in our Output Window. This query has returned us every single actor where
first_name = ‘Nick'. The implementation of comparison operators ‘equal to' is pretty straightforward.
Now we will see how operator ‘less than' works. Instead of using equal, in the WHERE clause I have used ‘less than'.
What it means is that now we will get all the actors who have ‘actor_id &lt; 100'. Let's select this query and Execute.
Now we have 99 rows and when we take the actor_id in resultset, you can clearly see that it is less than 99.
None of the actor_id is over 100. This is how we can use in our WHERE condition ‘less than' operator.
Let's execute this query and understand the result. Please pay special attention to the first_name when I
scroll over here. Very quickly, you will see the pattern that there is not a single name, which is starting with
any letter which comes after N in alphabet. Now let's understand ‘greater than' operator and we will understand
the same example a little bit more in depth. In our SELECT statement, in the WHERE condition, we have
‘actor_id &gt; 100'. Let's execute this and see the resultset. The query has returned 100 rows.
When we see the resultset, we can see actor_id starts at 100 and it goes all the way to 200.
Any record with actor_id less than 100 is no more included in this resultset. In case of the second query,
where we have first_name &gt; ‘Nick", select the statement and click on Execute. Now let's go to the resultset.
In this resultset, you can notice that every single name in the column first_name will be after NICK if
they're ordered alphabetically. However, in both the cases of ‘greater than' and ‘less than', we have noticed
that the actor_id 100 and first_name NICK was never included in the resultset. There can be a scenario where we
need actor_id 100, as well as first_name NICK also included as a part of the resultset. We can do that if we use
‘less than or equal to' operator. Let's see that in this case. In the result pane, let's scroll down all the way
and you can notice the very last_name is actor_id goes to 100. What it means is that this query has included 100
and every value which is less than 100 for actor_id. Similar logic also applies to first_name &lt;= ‘Nick'.
Let's select the statement and click on Execute. Now you can see that actor_id is equal to NICK is also included
in the resultset right away. Same logic also applies if you are going to use ‘greater than or equal to' operator.
Now, let's execute this query. You can see that we have now actor_id 100, as well as every actor_id over 100.
When I execute this query, any name alphabetically after NICK, as well as it includes first_name NICK.
Well, now you know how most of the comparison operators works. However, there is one more comparison operator,
which is very important to learn -- not equal to. Not equal to negates the condition, which we have provided into
WHERE clause. Let's understand that with an example. In this case, we have a condition where actor_id does not
equal to 100. What it means is that we'll get every single result ‘WHERE actor_id &lt;&gt; 100'. Let's execute this query
and we can see that now we have 199 rows in the resultset. If you scroll down and try to see between 99 and 101,
there is now row 100 because ‘actor_id = 100' should not be included in the resultset.
Similar case with ‘first_name != ‘Nick' as well. Let's execute this query and you can see NICK was actor_id 2.
It's not included in this query. If you scroll down all the way, you will not find names equal to NICK.
You will find resultset containing every other name besides NICK. Well, with this we complete our understanding
of comparison operators. Let's go to our next concept of logical operators.