So far we have seen in the WHERE condition that we are using simple such condition. What it means is that
we take one column name and try to compare it with string or integer literal.
However, the real world scenario is much more complex than this. We sometimes have more than one condition to
compare and validate. At that time, we need logical operators. Logical operators help WHERE condition to become
a compound condition. We can use multiple logical operators and can build a complex WHERE condition.
For example, here is the list of popular logical operators -- AND, OR, and NOT. AND operator is true if all the
conditions in WHERE clause are True. OR operator is True if any one of the conditions in WHERE clause is True,
whereas NOT is Negate Logic. What it means is that it will give us the logic, which we have used previously.
Sometimes NOT operators tend to confuse developers because of the issue. I suggest you write your logic
in such a way that you don't have to use NOT condition. Well, to understand this, we have to see a demo.
Let's open MySQL Workbench and see them into action.