Here, we are in MySQL Workbench in SQL Editor. Let's first see how AND operator works. Here is a simple example.
From sakila.actor table, we are going to retrieve all the records ‘WHERE first_name = ‘KENNETH'.
Select the statement, click on Execute, and you can see there are four rows retrieved over here.
Let's make it a little bit more complicated. In WHERE clause, we add one more condition and the condition is that
actor_id should be less than 100. Now if you carefully observe our resultset, you can see there are three records,
which are ‘actor_id &lt; 100', and one record, which has ‘actor_id &gt; 100'. Now, because of this new addition in the
WHERE clause, our resultset will not have four rows, but it should have three rows. Let's execute this and check
the resultset. Now it's very clear that in our resultset we don't have actor_id, which is greater than 100,
even though the first_name is KENNETH. Besides having ‘first_name = ‘KENNETH' AND ‘actor_id &lt; 100',
we have added one more condition where ‘last_name = ‘TORN'. Let's execute this and check the resultset.
In our entire table, this is the only row which satisfies all three conditions, which is specified in WHERE clause.
Now we will see how OR logic works. First, we will see a simple example and we will retrieve all the
records ‘first_name = ‘KENNETH'. Now you can see we have retrieved four rows. Let's make it a little bit more
complicated and we add one more OR into our WHERE clause. Right now, OR suggests ‘actor_id &lt; 100'.
What it means is that now our query should return everybody who has a ‘first_name = ‘KENNETH', as well
any ‘actor_id &lt; 100'. For example, looking at this condition, we know that following four rows will be part of
the resultset. When we look at this condition independently, we also understand that there will be additionally
99 rows also part of our resultset and there is always a chance of overlay. What it means is that we'll definitely
get all the record where ‘actor_id &lt; 100', as well as one additional row where ‘actor_id &gt; 100' and is 169 because
it qualifies for condition ‘WHERE first_name = ‘KENNETH'. Let's validate our assumption by executing this query
and let's scroll down. At the bottom of our resultset, we can see that we have retrieved every row,
which has ‘actor_id &lt; 99', as well retrieved row 169 because it has ‘first_name = ‘KENNETH' and that is also
one of OR condition. Now you can see in the WHERE clause we have added ‘last_name = ‘TEMPLE'.
What it means is that any row which has first_name as KENNETH or last_name as TEMPLE or ‘actor_id &lt; 100' will be
qualified for our resultset. Let's execute that and scroll all the way to the bottom. Now you can see that we
have additional rows where ‘last_name = ‘TEMPLE' and all of these rows have ‘actor_id &gt; 100'.
Well, now let's move to our next logical operator, which is NOT. Well, NOT conditions are very simple conditions.
They just negate the logic, which we have used in the WHERE clause. Let's see this example. Here, we will specify
‘actor_id = 50'. If we do not have a NOT, what it means is that this query will return as result
‘WHERE actor_id = 5'; however, because we have used NOT just right before our condition, what it means is that
this query will return us every single result where we don't have ‘actor_id = 5'. Let's exhibit this query and
relate it to our assumption. Well, in resultset, pay attention to actor_id column. There is no row between
actor_id 4 and actor_id 6. What it means is that this query does not return us any result where ‘actor_id = 5'.
Remember what I mentioned earlier? NOT sometimes confuses the user or developer if there is very
complicated logic. You can relate this query without using NOT as well. Look at this example.
Here, instead of using NOT, I have just changed the condition from ‘equal to' to ‘not equal to' and this query
will also return as absolutely same result. Now we have understood all three of our logical operators.
Now let's put all of them together and understand with much more complex examples. Here is our first example.
We will use AND and OR together. Let's execute this query and we have retrieved seven rows.
You can see this query has returned us everybody with the first_name as KENNETH and ‘actor_id &lt; 100'.
Additionally, it has also retrieved all the record where ‘last_name = ‘TEMPLE'. Remember, one more thing, which
we just discussed a few minutes ago, which is logical operator precedence. Logical operator precedence is NOT,
AND, and OR. What it means is that AND is evaluated first and OR is evaluated right after it.
In this case, two conditions were evaluated first and later, they were ordered with this condition.
Let's change this order of condition and we will see that we will get absolutely different result than what we
have just got over here. Now here is the second query. What we have done here is that we just took this OR and
moved it a little bit before AND and ‘AND actor_id' is now right after OR CONDITION. As for the precedence of
operator, AND will be evaluated first. What it means is that these two conditions will be evaluated first.
These two conditions will be evaluated first and later they will be ordered with ‘first_name = ‘KENNETH'.
Even though both the queries have almost similar conditions, they have very different meaning.
I selected the query and click on Execute. Now this query has returned as every record where ‘last_name = name'
and ‘actor_id &lt; 100'. What it means is that anybody who has a last name equal to TEMPLE, but actor_id is greater
than 100, is not part of this resultset. KENNETH is an OR condition so anybody who has a first name equal to
KENNETH will be always part of this resultset and, hence, we are able to see actor_id, which is 169, with
first_name as KENNETH also part of this resultset. The concept, which we have just discussed, is a very, very
important concept and I strongly encourage all of you to execute this query on a sakila Sample Database.
Now let's make it a little bit more complicated and take this example to the next level.
We'll start using parentheses to our logic, which we have just seen. Here are two examples.
Let's execute this first query first and you can notice this query is very similar to the OR initial query.
If you do not use parentheses in this logic, it will still give us same result. However, it's not true in this case.
You can notice over here we have parentheses around ‘(actor_id &lt; 100' OR ‘last_name = ‘TEMPLE')'.
When you select everything together and execute, you can see that we'll now only get the result
‘WHERE first_name = ‘KENNETH'. Funny enough, you want to build the condition ‘WHERE last_name = ‘TEMPLE',
none of the rows qualify because now we have additional conditions to our original resultset, which states
‘first_name = ‘KENNETH'. There is not a single actor who has last_name TEMPLE and first_name KENNETH.
Now you can see the power of parentheses and order of precedence, how they play together, and keep on changing
our result. Well, with this we end our logical operator section and let's move to the various other operators
related to WHERE condition.