WHERE clause is one of the most powerful clauses in entire SELECT statement. There are lots of interesting
elements, which we can use in the WHERE clause to make it interesting to learn. For example, IN phrase.
We can use IN phrase to test whether expression is equal to the value in the least. The order of element in
the least does not influence the final resultset. Additionally, we can use subquery in the IN clause as well.
During demonstration, we will quickly see an example of the same. In the advanced course, we will cover this
concept in detail. We can use NOT operator to negate the logic of IN phrase. BETWEEN phrase qualifies the row of
a resultset when an expression falls within the range. The lower and the upper limit range expressions are also
part of the range. Just like any other operator or phrase, we can use NOT to negate the resultset.
We can use LIKE operator to retrieve rows that matches a string pattern. A string pattern is called a mask.
We will also understand how Wildcard - % (percentage) and _ (underscore) helps to build this string pattern
using demonstration. Additionally, we can use NOT keyword before LIKE and negate the entire logic.
NULL is one of the most interesting concepts within Database. I have seen developers often getting confused
with NULL. Incorrect implementation of NULL brings unexpected results. NULL value stands for value that is
unknown or unavailable. It is not a 0 or not an infinite. In SQL, we can't compare NULL by using ‘equal to' operator.
We are to use special clause of IS NULL and IS NOT NULL. When we use this clause, our resultset contains value
based on this logic. Let's quickly jump to a demonstration and understand these concepts.