Let's open MySQL Workbench, SQL Editor, and let's start with our very first example.
First, we will understand how IN works. Once again, we will be using sakila.actor table.
‘SELECT * FROM sakila.actor WHERE first_name IN (‘NICK', ‘JOHNNY', ‘JOE', ‘VIVIEN')'. What it means is that this
query will return result where first_name is any of these names. Let's verify that. Select the statement and
click on Execute. The data type of our literals was string, that's why we have a single code around them and they're
all separated by comma. If the data type of our literal is integer, there is no need of single code around that.
Let's see an example of that as well. Here it is. In this case, we have literals as integers.
We do not need a single code around that. Our WHERE condition is ‘WHERE actor_id IN (1,2,3,4,5,6,7)'.
Let's select the statement and click on Execute. You can see in the resultset, we have all the result
‘WHERE actor_id' is (1,2,3,4,5,6,7). Well the implementation of IN is very simple as you can see that.
Now we will quickly see the example of the subquery. On a very first glance, we can see there are two different
queries over here. First query is that where we are ‘SELECTING * FROM sakila.actor WHERE first_name IN
(‘NICK', ‘JOHNNY', ‘JOE', ‘VIVIEN')' and there is an OR condition over here, which is looking for actor_id IN
and then the result of second query. Let's write now second query, which is
‘(SELECT actor_id FROM sakila.actor WHERE last_name = ‘DEGENERES')'. Let's execute this query and see what is the
resultset. When we run this resultset, we can see it returns us three distinct values, which is 41, 107, and 166.
What it means is that there are three actors whose last_name is DEGENERES and their actor_id is 41, 107, and 166.
That simplifies this query a lot. What it means is that ‘SELECT * FROM sakila.actor WHERE first_name IN
(‘NICK', ‘JOHNNY', ‘JOE', ‘VIVIEN') OR actor_id IN (41, 107, 166). What it means is that we will get every record
where first_name is either NICK, JOHNNY, JOE or VIVIEN. Additionally, there will be rows where actor_id will be
41, 107, and 166. To evaluate our assumption, let's select entire query and click on Execute.
Carefully observe the first_name column of the resultset. You can see the name belongs to NICK, JOHNNY, JOE or
VIVIEN. Additionally, there should be three record where actor_id's go to 41, 107, and 166.
In case of the actor_id 41, we can clearly see it's over here, actor_id 2, 5, 9, 14, and 40, the logic was
first_name belonged to our four names. In case of the actor_id 41, the last_name was DEGENERES and that's the
reason it qualified for this resultset. Same logic is for 107 as well. This record qualifies for both of the
conditions. What it means is that, if we had a condition instead of OR and here, actor_id 166 will be still
a valid resultset. Instead of OR right here, AND. Now, we will execute this and you can see only one record
is now in our resultset. This record is here because the first_name is NICK and the last_name is DEGENERES.
Now let's understand how BETWEEN clause works, but before that let's execute a simple query.
‘SELECT * FROM sakila.actor WHERE actor_id &gt; 10 AND actor_id &lt; 20'. What it means is that it will get us every
single actor_id, which is over 10 and less than 20. Let's select this and execute it. In the resultset, we have
nine rows where actor_id is from 11 to 19.
Here is an example: ‘SELECT * FROM sakila.actor WHERE actor_id BETWEEN 10 AND 20'. Now let's select this one
and execute. When we execute this record, we can see that there are no more nine rows. The total number of the
rows are 11. The difference between this query and the query, which we ran before, are row with actor_id 10 and
row with actor_id 20. The reason is that the way the BETWEEN works is that it also includes both the ranges.
What it means is that the 10 is also part of the range and 20 is also part of the range.
The way the range logic works, in case of the BETWEEN is, lower range, upper range, and anything between them.
If you want to simulate this query with using BETWEEN, you will have to change here something.
Instead of 10, you are to replace that by 11 and instead of 20, you are to replace that by 19.
Now, this query will be exactly similar to the query, which we have executed in the beginning just like this.
Let's go further down. You can just put NOT before BETWEEN and it will just negate the complete logic over here.
With the use of NOT keyword here, you will get every single row where actor_id is lower than 11 and actor_id
is greater than 19. Let's evaluate that. Select the statement and click on Execute. Now let's go further down
and you can see after 10, right after there is a value of 20. There is no other value in-between.
It means rows with actor_id 11 and more and rows with actor_id 19 and less are all omitted. You can see the BETWEEN
can be very powerful when we have to deal with range.