Now we will see how LIKE operator works.
LIKE is very powerful and interesting because it works with patterns. Using pattern logic and Wildcard, you can
pretty much build infinite combinations of the logic to use in a WHERE condition and let's start a few of
them over here. Here are some of the examples.
The first one is ‘SELECT * FROM sakila.actor WHERE first_name LIKE ‘A%'. This one pretty much will list every
single actor whose first_name starts with A. Percentage means there's just one or more characters.
Let's execute this one and you can see in our resultset, we have every single actor whose first_name starts with A.
However, if you want to make it a little bit more interesting, we can select only actor whose first_name starts
with A and L, which means we should get ALEC, ALBERT. ALBERT is here two times, which means actor_id 125 and
actor_id 146 should be also part of our result. Let's execute this one and we will see.
Here, we have WHERE condition ‘WHERE first_name LIKE ‘AL%'. In resultset, we have all the actors whose
first_name now starts with AL. Well, we can make it more clarity as well. Here is an example.
Here, we have used two underscores. Underscore stands for a single character. The pattern, which we have
returned here, is the first character is A, second and third can be any other character; however, the fourth
character has to be E. Let's exhibit this one and see how many records qualify for this pattern.
When we execute this, we can only find one actor who qualifies for this kind of pattern, that is ANNE, because the
first character is A, we do not get about second and third character, however, the fourth character has to be E.
Additionally, when we write this kind of pattern, it means we are looking for a four-character string only.
However, if we just put percentage right after it, now what it means is that we can have first character A,
second and third we don't get; however, the fourth character must be E. When we put percentage right after E,
it means now we don't care how long this particular string is. Well, let's execute this one and see if we find
any actor with such a name. You can find there are many, ANGELA, ANGELINA, ALBERT, ANGELA, and ALBERT again,
along with our original record of ANNE. You can see in all of these there is a single pattern.
First character is A, fourth character is E; however, we do not get the length of them, as well as we do not get
what is the second and third character is. Let's further continue to modify the same pattern.
Here, instead of putting two underscores, now we have replaced two underscores with single percentage.
Now what it means is that the first character is A and there is a percentage between A and E.
What it means is that E doesn't have to be anymore the fourth character, E can be any character after A,
and there can be any number of the characters between A and E and we do not care about them.
Additionally, E does not have to be the fourth and last character, there can be more characters right after
percentage as well. What it means is that, find the name, but start with A and has E anywhere in the name
except for splits. Let's execute this one and you can find many of the records. Now we can see the position
of E is not fixed, in this case it's third and in this case it's second to last. Again, in the case of ANNE,
it's the fourth and in the case of ANGELA, it is also fourth. Well, now there is no real logic where the E is
going to be; however, you can notice that A is always the first character. Now let's go to our next concept,
which about NULL. As we said, NULL is very interesting and it's very important to understand how NULL's behave.
We cannot use any arithmetic or logical operators over NULL. To compare NULL, you just have to use special keyword,
which is IS NULL or IS NOT NULL. Let's go to our address table and select every single record from it.
You can see in column address2, there are four records which are NULL and other records have empty string.
Let's go to our second query and run it. Please pay special attention here, the WHERE condition is address2 IS NULL.
What it means is that every record where address 2 IS NULL, should be part of the resultset.
Select the query and execute it and you can see that our four records over here where address2 IS NULL.
If you want to make it this condition, select the query and execute and now you will get every single row where
address2 IS NOT NULL. Well, logical to NULL is very interesting and now starts playing a very crucial role when
we start using outer joins. With this, we finish our demonstration regarding WHERE clause.
Now we will go to our next concept of ORDER BY clause.