Now you open MySQL Workbench and SQL Editor. We will be seeing examples of how ORDER BY works.
Let's start with a very simple example, here it is, ‘SELECT * FROM sakila.address ORDER BY district'.
Select the statement and click on Execute. In the resultset, pay attention to the distinct column.
You can notice that the distinct column is now ordered alphabetically in ascending order.
Abu Chabi is on the top and Zulia at the end. Now, if you want to reverse the order of this column, what it means
is that you want Zulia on the top and Abu Chabi on the bottom. You can easily do it if you just specify
descending keyword in an ORDER BY clause. Here is the example. Let's select the statement and click on Execute.
You can see that now Zulia is on the top and if you scroll all the way to bottom, Abu Chabi is at the end.
Now let's see another example where we have more than one column in ORDER BY clause. Let's select this one and Execute.
Let's take the example of Abu Chabi itself. You can see that Abu Chabi is on the top. It is ordered in ascending
sequence by column distinct. If you pay attention to the postal_code, you can see that the higher number is on
the top and lower number is on the bottom. What it means is that in this window of Abu Chabi, MySQL has once
again sorted postal_codes. However, the order of the postal_code is descending, hence, you can see the value,
which is higher on the top and the value, which is lower on the bottom. Similar example is also here in Adna.
You can see that higher number is on the top, where lower number in the postal_code column is on the bottom.
Now, let's see a different example. Here it is, where we have our expression in a SELECT statement.
You can see that here we have actor_id from sakila.actor table and we are concatenating first_name and last_name
and we are aliasing first_name and last_name as FullName. We can order this complete table by expression using
the SELECT statement. For example, we can use this concat in our ORDER BY clause as well.
Let's select this complete statement and Execute. You can see that now complete table is now ORDER BY expression,
which you have specified in ORDER BY clause. To make things simple, we can also use alias in ORDER BY clause as well.
You can see here that instead of using expression, we are using the alias, which we have given in SELECT statement
in ORDER BY clause. Let's select this one and click on Execute. The resultset is very similar to the one we
called; however, it's very easy to read and easy to write as, instead of writing complete expression, we can
just replace it with alias. Well, there is one more trick I want to show you. Here, in ORDER BY, we have
used digit 2. Digit 2 stands for column #2, which is in a SELECT statement. What it means is that actor_id is
column 1 and concat expression is column 2. Let's exhibit this one. You can see that our resultset is ORDER BY
second column, which is concatenating of first_name and last_name. If we remove these two and put over here 1,
it will be ORDER BY actor_id. Let's see that. Select the statement, click on Execute, and you can see that now
complete resultset is ORDER BY actor_id column. Well, personally I do not like this method because this method
can create ambiguity when we are using the * or when we have a schema change or some developer adds column in
a SELECT clause. I personally prefer to use complete expression or alias of the column in ORDER BY clause.
Well with this, we finish our understanding of ORDER BY clause.