Now we have reached to very last concept, which we want to learn in this module, which is LIMIT clause.
We can use LIMIT clause to limit the number of the rows that are returned by SELECT statement.
This clause usually has one or two arguments. Each of them has different meaning and we will understand them
while we do demonstration. It's always recommended that we use ORDER BY along with LIMIT because there is no
guarantee when we use LIMIT that we are going to get the data in the same order in every subsequent execution
of the same SELECT statement. The frequent use of this LIMIT clause is when we are doing paging.
Think about it this way. If there are 1000 rows in one table and now you want to retrieve only row, which is
between 500 and 510, how would you go about retrieving them? Well, this is the time that you use the LIMIT clause
because LIMIT clause has a two-argument, one is number of the rows and second one is offset.
Let's quickly understand both of them in demonstration.