Here we are in MySQL Workbench in SQL Editor and we are going to see how LIMIT keyword works.
As mentioned earlier, LIMIT keyword is a pretty straightforward keyword. Let's first retrieve data from
sakila.actor, where we have ORDER BY clause on actor_id. Let's go and apply LIMIT 10. What it does is that when
we execute this statement, it will only retrieve 10 rows; however, what happens if you want to retrieve data,
which is somewhere in-between the table? What it means is that you want to retrieve row #30 to 35 or row #50 to 65.
At that time, you can additionally specify offset to the LIMIT clause. This is how it works. Look at this example
where we have LIMIT 15 and 10. Well, these have two parameters. Let's execute them and understand what each of
these parameters do. When you execute this query, you can see that the first record is no more actor_id 1,
it is now actor_id 16. The first parameter, which we provided to LIMIT keyword, is offset. What it means is that
if you specify you had 15, MySQL would skip first 15 lines and would start reading the lines after that.
Here, if I specify 10, what it means is that is only going to retrieve 10 rows. Let's change this number and see
one more example. For that, I'm going to put here 25 and number of the rows I'm going to put 5.
What it will do is that it will start retrieving rows from row #26 and will retrieve till row #30 because we are
going to retrieve only five rows. Now, let's select this one and click on Execute. As we expected, it is
retrieving us five rows from the actor_id 26 and onwards. As LIMIT clause limits the number of the rows it
retrieves from the offset, it also helps with performance of overall server health. Well, with this we end our
understanding of data retrieval and it's various clauses, phrase, and operators. In the next module, we will see
data modification techniques and now we end this module with summary in sixty seconds.