Now, let's see some of the SELECT statement into action. We will go over some of the basic and simple
SELECT statements in the beginning, later we will see more complicated examples. First, we will see how we can
use SELECT statement to retrieve static values. Later, we will use SELECT statement to retrieve all the data from
table using star. The same retrieved data, we will order by single column. Later, we will only select
selected columns instead of all the column from the table. Right after that, we will make sure the data,
which we will retrieve, is not all the data. We will write a filter condition on the top of the SELECT statement
and retrieve only selected rows. After that, we will combine all of our learning and retrieve data for
selected column using filter condition and with order by multiple columns. Finally, we will see a simple trick
where we will retrieve empty resultset using SELECT statement. Now let's see a demonstration where we will see
each of them in action. Now let's open MySQL Workbench.