Well, open MySQL Workbench and let's start with simple examples. As discussed in an earlier set of clip,
you just need sakila Sample Database, MySQL Workbench, and MySQL Server. Let's start coding together.
Let's type ‘SELECT MyFirstValue'. MyFirstValue is a string and let's select that and see what result comes up.
Click on Execute and you can see MyFirstValue is now displayed over here. The name of the column is same as the
value as we have not specified any alias. Let's type alias ‘AS SomeValue'. Now let's execute the same thing
again and you can see name of the column is now SomeValue and value is MyFirstValue. Similar thing you can do with
arithmetic operations over here. SELECT 1+1 and let's see the fun. You can see that value is now 2 because 1+1 is 2;
however, name of the column is 1+1. Let's give it alias over here ‘AS TWO'. Now let's execute it one more time
and you can see now name of the column is TWO and the value is also TWO. In MySQL, you can also get current date/time
by using function NOW. Let's learn SELECT NOW. The result displays with current date and time.
If you just want only date part and not the time part, you can just write ‘SELECT CURDATE'.
Let's execute this and you can see only date part is displayed and time part is not displayed anymore.
If you want only time, similar way you can write ‘SELECT CURTIME' and it will display as current time and
date part is not displayed. You can also display the value of pi by using ‘SELECT PI' files in BUILD function.
Let's execute it and you can see the value of pi is displayed here, 3.141593. Well, you can do other mathematical
functions as well, like finding remainder. When you divide 45 by 7, what will be the remainder?
Well, let's learn ‘SELECT MOD(45,7)' and it gives us remainder as 3. Another interesting function would be to
just find square root of any value. Here, we have specified 25 and square root of 25 is 5.
Let's execute this and you can see it has found square root of 25, it is 5. You do not need FROM, WHERE,
ORDER BY clauses if you are just doing some simple operations.