Now we will see how we can use star and retrieve all the data from the table.
Here is an example, ‘SELECT * FROM sakila.actor'. When we use a star and do not provide any filter condition
using WHERE, this statement will retrieve every single column and every single row from sakila.actor table.
Select the statement and click on Execute. You can see it is retrieving all the four columns and all the 200 rows
from sakila.actor table. Let's take another example. We can also retrieve all the rows and all the columns from
sakila.city table. Select the statement and click on Execute. Well if you noticed, we are using sakila.city name.
This naming convention is database.tablename. If you don't want to keep on using sakila in a name of this table,
you can use another technique. For example, here I'm using ‘USE sakila'. When we execute this statement,
it will by default sakila database as a database for every subsequent execution of statement.
Let's see that into action, but first, pay attention on the left side in Object Browser.
You can see sakila, test, and world, all three have similar fonts. Now, let's execute ‘USE sakila'.
When you execute this one, at that time, now sakila is highlighted or bold. What it means is that now sakila
is default context for every single execution after this statement. When we execute this one, it will retrieve as
same data, which we got from ‘SELECT * FROM sakila.city'. USE database name is a good idea to execute if you know
every subsequent execution you are going to do from same database. Let's close this and now in the next clip,
we will retrieve all of the data ordered by single column. (Typing)