Now we will see how we can retrieve all the data ordered by single column.
For example, here is ‘SELECT * FROM sakila.actor', which we have just sent. It has four columns -- actor_id,
first_name, last_name, and last_update. Quickly glancing at resultset, we can see that first_name column is not
ordered alphabetically, so is last_name. We can quickly order first_name in alphabetical, chronological order if
we write ‘ORDER BY first_name' right after SELECT statement. Let's select this statement and execute it.
Now we can see that first_name is chronologically ordered, ADAM is first, ZERO is at last.
Interesting enough, the name of actor is ZERO. Similar way, we can order the same table with last_name.
Let's execute this statement. Now you can see that the complete table is ordered by last_name column.
A is on the top and C is at the bottom. Well, currently we had just seen them in alphabetical order; however,
the order is ascending. We can also change this sequence order by just adding DESC clause.
Let's execute this first statement where we have first_name as descending in ORDER BY clause.
When we execute that, we can see now ZERO is on the top and ADAM is on the bottom. What happens here is that
by adding ORDER BY, column name, and DESC clause, now entire table is ordered descending by first_name column.
We can do similar thing with last_name as well. Let's execute this statement and now, entire table is
‘ORDER BY last_name DESC'. ORDER BY clause is very handy and very easy to use. Now in the next clip, we will see how we
can retrieve selected columns from table.