So far we have been retrieving all of the  columns and all the rows from the table.
Now we will see how we can retrieve only selected columns instead of retrieving all the columns.
For example, let's see ‘SELECT * FROM sakila.actor'. There are four columns -- first is actor_id, second is
first_name, last_name, and last one is last_update. Now it's quite possible not everybody needs last_update data.
Some people may only want to see first_name and last_name. Well, we can do that very easily, instead of writing *,
we can just write first_name and last_name and select data from this table.
We will write SELECT first_name, last_name FROM table name, which is sakila.actor. Let's select this and execute.
Now you can see we are getting data from only two columns, which first_name and last_name.
There are many reasons to spell column names instead of writing *; however, the primary reason for that
is performance. Additionally note, the data which we retrieve for first_name and last_name is not in order.
If you want to order them, we can just specify ORDER BY clause over here.
In this case, I'm specifying ‘ORDER BY first_name DESC'. Let's select this statement and execute it.
Now we have first_name and last_name column, ORDER BY first_name DESC. In this example, we have seen how we can
filter columns and retrieve only the columns which we need. In next demonstration, we will see how we can further
filter rows as well.