In the real example, we filter columns; in this example, we will filter rows.
‘SELECT * FROM table name' retrieves every single row and column from table. You can see that in this example where
I'm retrieving all the data from sakila.actor table. Here, let me introduce a new clause, which is WHERE clause.
WHERE clause is nothing but condition. In later part of this module only, we will understand WHERE clause in
detail; however, this is a simple example. Let's write the statement from the start.
SELECT * FROM sakila.actor; what it means is that now we are going to get every single row and every single column
from sakila.actor table. Now, let's read the next line, ‘WHERE actor_id &gt; 100'. What it means is that now we will
only retrieve from sakila.actor table, those rows where actor_id is greater than 100.
Currently, our sakila.actor table has 200 rows. Now we are talking about retrieving rows only where actor_id
is greater than 100. Let's select this statement and execute it. You can see that in the result, our data
starts from actor_id 101. Let's quickly scroll down and see if there are any data which is less than 100.
A quick inspection demonstrates that there are no rows which has actor_id greater than 100. What it means is that
this WHERE condition has filtered out row where actor_id is 100 or less. Now let's change this greater than to
less than and see what result it brings to us. After executing, we can see that we have actor_id 1; however, let's
see what is our maximum actor_id. The maximum is 99 because here, we have WHERE condition where we have specified
that ‘WHERE actor_id &lt; 100'. You can notice that writing WHERE condition is very simple and it's very intuitive.
Let's see the next example. In this example, now we are filtering out fourth column, which is last_update.
We are only selecting actor_id, first_name, and last_name. We have changed here the WHERE condition, now I'm
mentioning WHERE first_name = ‘Nick'. What it means is that now we will enter only those rows,
WHERE first_name = ‘Nick' from the table sakila.actor. Let's select this statement and execute it.
We can see there are three records over here. All three records have first_name as ‘Nick'; however, last_name
is different. Additionally, the fourth column of last_updated is also not visible over here.
It was very easy to see how we can filter rows and columns. (Typing)