Hi, this is Pinal Dave for Pluralsight. In this module, we will talk about Summary and Resources.
So far, we have learned Installation of MySQL Server, MySQL Workbench, and MySQL Sample Databases.
All of these components and all other components are installed by default.
Later, we learned MySQL Workbench and three of its major sections -- SQL Development, where we connected to
existing database and ran SQL queries; Data Modeling, where we created and managed EER models;
Server Administration, where we configured Database Server and set up user accounts.
Later, we spent time on Relational Database Management System and Database Design Concepts.
We also learned in depth various techniques for data retrieval. In Data Retrieval Techniques, we focused on
SELECT, WHERE, ORDER BY, and LIMIT clauses. Finally, we spent a lot of time on Data Modification Techniques.
We learned how we can modify our data using INSERT, UPDATE, and DELETE.
Well, here are a few of the important resources.
Well, I thank you very, very much for spending time learning with me, MySQL Fundamentals Part 1.
In Part 2 of MySQL Introduction, we will learn Joins, Functions, Views, Transactions, Stored Procedures,
Stored Functions, Triggers and Events. Thank you and we will meet in MySQL Introduction Part 2.