Now we will see how we can view and edit column definition in SQL Editor. Go to SQL Development Area.
Click on your server and it will open SQL Editor. We will be using sakila simple database for this example.
Let's expand it and further expand Tables section. On the very first table, which is actor, right-click over it
and now click on Alter Table. Alter Table will open up this screen where we can complete table definition.
We can see there are four columns over here -- the actor_id, first_name, last_name, and last_update.
Additionally, we can see each Column Name's Datatype as well. Actor_id is SMALLINT, first_name is VARCHAR,
last_name is VARCHAR, and last_update is a TIMESTAMP. If you remember, we talked about there are various
properties of Column. Now we can also set them over here. First column, PK stands for Primary Key.
Actor_id in this table is a Primary Key. The second column is Not Null column. You can see that actor_id,
first_name, last_name, and last_update are Not Null columns. The next column UQ stands for Unique Index.
There is no Unique Index in this table. BIN stands for Binary. If any of the column was binary, the checkbox
in front of that column would have been selected. UN stands for Unsigned Datatype. In this case, small integer is
Unsigned Datatype. Also, there are two additional properties, which we have talked earlier.
One of them was Default Value. You can also select Default Value over here. ZF -- ZF stands for ‘Fill up value
for that column with 0 if it is numeric'. If any of this column is numeric, we can just select this particular
column and it will automatically default it to 0. AI stands for Auto Increment. In this case, the first column,
actor_id, it is also a Primary Key and it is also auto incremented. If you remember, in a previous module
we talked about most of the time the column which is auto incrementing is a good candidate for Primary Key.
If there is any other Default Value, we can also specify them over here. For example, in the fourth column,
which is last_update, we have a TIMESTAMP datatype and it is Not Null and the Default Value is CURRENT_TIMESTAMP.
What it means is that when we insert any row in this table, if we do not specify what data goes to last_update,
we will automatically assume CURRENT_TIMESTAMP value, which is current date/time. You can further see
the translation of each of these columns in this area. If you carefully look over here, you can see there are
other tabs as well. The Index tab talks about what kind of index exists on this particular table.
We can also create new indexes, as well as delete indexes over here. We can use this Foreign Key tab to define
Foreign Key between this table and another table. If there are any triggers, they will be listed over here and
we can further modify them. If the table is partitioned, you can see the logic over here.
We will talk about partitioning in Administration Course and on the last tab, we can set up various different
values for Table. For example, here we can specify the Auto Increment Value. This is the new initial
Auto Increment Value for the table. If you have 1000 record in this table, the next record will be 1001
and remember to click on Apply if you want to commit any changes you do with table definition.