Now we will see how we can use Snippet in MySQL Workbench. Snippets are nothing but a library of SQL Syntax.
No matter how expert you are writing SQL queries, there are always moments when we don't remember what was
the exit syntax of a particular feature. To enter the Snippet Area, go onto MySQL Workbench on the further
right-most icon over here. Click here and it will open up Snippet Area. Let's see a few of the Snippets.
Double-click on SELECT Syntax and you can see the SELECT Syntax is given over here. You can either edit this one
and write new syntax over here and click on Done. Similar way, we have a JOIN, INSERT, UPDATE, DELETE, and
REPLACE Syntax. Let's try to create a Snippet for selecting data from a table. I'll write down syntax over here,
which is SELECT * FROM. Now I will select this one and click on Add snippet. When I click on this one, you can
see there is a new entry over here. Now double-click on it and you can see the selected text is visible here,
which is SELECT * FROM. Now click on Done again and now type any schema name followed by a table name.
For example, sakila.actor. Now right-click over the snippet and select ‘Insert snippet text' at the cursor
and you can see it automatically populated SELECT * FROM and table name, which we had already written.
You can just click on SELECT and now it will display the data. This is how you can use snippet to expedite
writing your SQL queries.