So far we have been seeing features from SQL Development section. Let us see how Data Modeling section works.
We'll create an EER Model from existing database. Let's click over here and select our preferred connection.
I'll select SQLAuthority, click on Next, and it has successfully connected to DBMS. Additionally, it has also
retrieved schema lists from database. Click on Next and you can see all the schema which exists in MySQL Database.
Let's select sakila and click on Next. You can see on this screen that it has successfully retrieved all the
object from sakila schema. Click on Next. On this page, it is asking us, what are the objects which we want to
use for reverse engineering? We can select Tables, Views, Routines, and Trigger. Just for this example, I will
leave all of them checked and click on Execute. You can see that it has successfully executed
reverse engineering task. Click on Next and we can see the Success Message. Now, for last time, click on Finish.
Here is our EER diagram. Well, currently all the objects are over each other. Let's select all of them by
typing CTRL A. Now go to Arrange and click on Autolayout. It will automatically layout each of these tables,
along with their relationships. Let's go to city table and click on Indexes. Click on Indexes and you can see
there is only a Primary Key over here. EER diagrams are very interesting to read. Let's go back to the main screen
of MySQL Workbench.