Now let's understand a couple of important features of MySQL Server Administration.
Double-click on the connection, which we have already created, and it will open Server Administration Area.
On the top of the screen, it displays Server Status. You can see in this INFO section that the name of our Server
is SQLAuthority and it is running on a Local Host. Additionally, resin of the Server is also 5.6.10.
The status of our Server is Running. On the very right side, you can see the system has both CPU and memory.
MySQL Server Health is also displayed right beside it. Connection, Traffic, Query Cache Hit Ratio,
and Key Efficiency are displayed here. We can quickly see them and get an idea of how Server Health is.
Also, you can see there are four different connections and each connection has a different state.
One connection has a Query and the other three connections are right now in the sleeping state.
If there is Query, which is taking a lot of resources, you can either kill the query or can kill the complete
connection as well. Right below Server Status, there is Startup and Shut Down option.
You can stop your MySQL Server from here, as well as start it. Let's stop our server and start again.
Currently, the Server Status is Running. Click on Stop Server and now you can see the server instance is stopped.
If you want to start the server instance back, you can just click on Start Server and it will turn on
MySQL Server instance. You can use this administration screen to do a lot of other tasks as well.
For example, you can collect Status and System Variables or you can see Server Logs. If there are any errors,
you can find them over here. Additionally, you can configure MySQL Administration's lots of variable over here.
There are many important settings in this Configuration Area. In MySQL Administration course, we'll go over each
of these options and their significance. We'll discuss about Logging, InnoDB, Networking, Advanced settings,
Other settings, Security-related settings, Application, MyISAM, and Performance-related settings.
I often see developers working hard to tune the SQL queries; however, they absolutely ignored this
Performance Tab in MySQL Administration. There are many options available in this Configuration Area,
which can immediately impact performance very positively. This Server Administration Area also gives you
fine control on your Users and their Privilege. You can take a backup and export to database or import your
database and restore your MySQL Database from this Data Export/Restore section. Let's click on Home Tab and go
to the main screen of MySQL Workbench. Well, with this, we'll finish our introduction to MySQL Workbench.