Now we understand the three major sections of MySQL Workbench -- SQL Development, Data Modeling,
and Server Administration. Now we will understand Workbench Central. Click over here and you can see there are
various links for Workbench Central. The first one is MySQL Doc Library. Click over here and it will open
MySQL Documentation. You can pretty much search anything over here and this is a great reference.
For example, let's search for ‘alter index' and when we search for alter index, it gives us 24 matches and all of them
showed up instantaneously. Let's do another search. Let's search for ‘create database'. There are more than 50
results for ‘create database'. If you are doing MySQL code and if you're stuck, I strongly encourage you to
refer to MySQL Workbench Reference Manual. There is a good chance that it will solve all of your problems.
Let's close this and go to Home Page.
The second link over here is MySQL Utility. When we click over here, it displays us a list of MySQL Utilities.
They are very important. For example, there are utilities for identifying difference, auditing administration
or doing import or export. Let's close it and here is the link for Database Migration.
When you click over here, it opens MySQL Workbench Migration Wizard. This wizard assists us in migrating table
and data from supported database system to MySQL. You can also use this one to copy database from one
MySQL instance to another MySQL instance. Let's close this one.
Similarly, we can submit MySQL Bug from MySQL Workbench itself, as well as for additional tips and tricks,
we can read Workbench blogs. Now we are back on the main screen of MySQL Workbench. With this, we conclude this
module and move to Summary.