MySQL Workbench feature list is very long. It will be impossible to cover every single feature in this module.
We will be covering the features which we are going to use in this course, as well as the essential feature,
which is important to do any task in your daily job. MySQL Workbench features can be divided in following areas:
Database Development, Database Designing, Database Administration, Database Migration, and Miscellaneous.
You can see that MySQL Workbench is very feature-rich and pretty much you can do every single task,
which you need to do with MySQL Database. In Database Development Area, you can do schema browsing,
syntax highlighting, addition or update to the result set, as well as it contains efficiency tool of snippets.
Database Designing, it is a very critical task for any database developer. MySQL Workbench offers visual
Drag'n'Drop modeling. It also helps to reverse engineering from SQL Scripts, as well as from live database.
Schema synchronization and printing of models are also very popular Database Designing features of
MySQL Workbench. In Database Administration, one can configure any instance, as well as do account management.
You can turn on or turn off any database instance, as well as do log file browsing.
Additionally, you can use MySQL Workbench for Database Migration, but you can use any ODBC compliant database
to migrate from one database to another database. Well, this was just a list of MySQL Workbench features.
Let's see MySQL Workbench into action next.