Now for the rest of the module, we will see demonstration of MySQL Workbench features, which will be useful to us
in performing of a daily task with MySQL. You can start MySQL Workbench on Windows platform by going to
Start &gt;&gt; All Programs &gt;&gt; MySQL &gt;&gt; (and clicking on) MySQL Workbench application. Upon launching MySQL Workbench,
you will see following screen. This is the home screen of MySQL Workbench. On the home screen of MySQL Workbench,
we have three major workspaces or sections - First is SQL Development, second Data Modeling, and third is
Server Administration. SQL Development is the section where we'll be spending most of our time as this is
a SQL Development course. In the SQL Development Area, we can create databases and run SQL queries.
In Data Modeling, we will create and manage models. Additionally, we also reverse engineer database.
In the Server Administration Area, we can set up various user accounts, browse status variables and server logs.
We can also do important export of the data over here. You will also see how we can start and shut down Server
in this section. On the top part, you can see Workbench Central. Click on the arrow and it will expand.
We have few of the very important links in Workbench Central Area, like MySQL Document Library, MySQL Utilities,
Database Migration, MySQL Bug Reporter, as well as Workbench Blogs. Let's start first with SQL
Development Workspace.