In the SQL Development Area, first we will learn about how to open a new connection and
start creating a database. Go to the Open Connection screen, click over here. On this Connect to Database screen,
we'll be providing a few of the information so we can connect to the database. First, we will give a Host name.
I have provided 127.0.0.1 because this is my local host and MySQL Server is installed here on a local host with
default Port of 3306. The Username is Root. Now click here for Password. On the Password page, enter the
password which you provided and then we install MySQL. Click OK. Now click on OK again.
You can see that it has opened SQL Editor for us. Let's go back to home screen before we continue with SQL Editor.
Now you've seen here how we can open a connection and start querying, but we are all developers and we know that.
There are a few connections, which we like to save and keep on using it again and again.
We can also save connections in the SQL Development Area. Let's see that how we can do that.
Click on New Connection and it will bring up this screen. Go right over here, Connection Name, and provide
information for Host Name, Port, Username, and Password. Click OK and now on this screen, you can also
paste connection. Click on Paste Connection and it will show us the status of our connection and click on
OK one more time. Now over here you can see the SQLAuthority is a new connection, it is saved.
You can double-click over here and it will also open SQL Query Editor. Now we have two tabs in our SQL Editor.
First tab, which we opened a few minutes ago and second tab, which we just opened.
On the second tab, you can clearly see it is marked with SQLAuthority label. These labels are very important.
I've seen an industry that Developer has executed incorrect SQL on a wrong server with the wrong connection.
Well, before you execute anything, always make sure the label of the connection is correct.