Well, we just noticed that we have created a new connection, which is SQLAuthority. As you keep on using MySQL
in your production environment and development environment, you will notice that the number of the connections
you work with keep on increasing. At one point, you may want to delete, create or modify your existing connection.
You can easily manage all of the connections from your MySQL Workbench. Under SQL Development Area, go to
Manage Connections and click over here. It will bring up this screen. You can see on the left side there is a
SQLAuthority connection. This is the only connection we have created so far. Let's click over here.
Once we clicked, you can see all the information from this connection is filled up on the right side.
You can also configure a few of the advanced connections over here by clicking over Advanced Tab.
As this is a fundamental course, we will be not spending much of the time on this tab. Let's go back on Parameters.
Also on the bottom of the screen, you can see there are a few options -- New creates new connection,
Delete deletes existing connection. Let's create one more connection. I'll click on New and new connection is
isolated on the left side, as well as it has populated few of the default value on the right side of the screen.
Let's give Connection Name as Pluralsight. We'll give Connection Method as a Standard (TCP/IP).
In the Host Name, I would reckon leave this one as it is or we can provide Local Host as a Host Name.
We'll keep Username, Root, and the Password. Click OK and in this case, we'll also give a Default Schema.
We will use Default Schema as sakila. Now, let's click on Test Connection and our test is successful.
Click OK and now you can close this one. On the main screen, you can see that now we have two databases,
one is SQLAuthority and second one is Pluralsight. Let's change the order of SQLAuthority and Pluralsight in
Manage Connection. Click on Manage Connection and now let's click on Pluralsight on the left side in
Stored Connection area and click on Move Up. You can see that Pluralsight is now on the top and SQLAuthority
is on bottom. Click Close and on the main screen, the order is also changed. Now double-click on newly created
Pluralsight connection and you can notice that sakila is highlighted. What it means is that sakila database is
now by default selected. Now let's go back to home screen.