Now we will see how we can use MySQL Workbench to edit table data. On the home screen of MySQL Workbench,
go to Edit Table Data. I'll select SQLAuthority as my stored connection and we'll click on Next.
Over here, it will give us a few dropdowns where we can select our default schema and tables.
I'll select default schema as sakila and table as actor. You can select other table if you prefer.
Now click on Finish. Immediately it has opened up table, actor. You can also see name of the table over here, actor.
Now let's go to the very first row and you can see the first row is edit table. You can change the value if you prefer.
I'll leave this actor_id as 1; however, instead of PENELOPE, I will put over here PENELOPE1. Now click on tab.
Instead of GUINESS, I will also put over here GUINESS1. I'll move to line #3 and over here I'll put ED2
and behind CHASE I'll put 2 again. You can see that now I have edited totals. Now you can see on the screen that
I have changed PENELOPE to PENELOPE1 and GUINESS to GUINESS1. Do you think this information is committed?
What I mean by that is that if I go back and select this data again, do you think I will see PENELOPE and GUINESS
or I will see PENELOPE1 and GUINESS1? Well, let's go back and check it in Query Editor. Now to write a new query,
go to SQL Editor and click on ‘Create a new SQL tab for executing queries'. It will open Code Editor Tab.
Now let's type in a simple query. After selecting the query, click on lightning bolt icon over here.
It will execute the selected portion of the script or everything if there is no selection. Click here and you can
see the result is now displayed in Visual Tab. On Visual Tab, let's look at the first row.
First row says PENELOPE and GUINESS. Remember we have changed them to PENELOPE1 and GUINESS1.
We expect to see the changes over here, but they are not over here. The reason is very simple.
Let's go back to our actor tab and over here you can still see them, PENELOPE1 and GUINESS1.
Though we have changed the record over here, we are not committed yet. What it means is that the
data which have you seen as changed is only in the Query Editor. They are still not propagated to an
actual database. To apply them to the actual database, you have to select on Apply.
You can see on the right bottom screen, there is an Apply tab, which is highlighted. Now let's click on Apply.
Apply asks us to give you two updates. You can see over here it has automatically generated two update scripts.
One is UPDATE ‘sakila'.'actor' SET where ‘first_name' is PENELOPE1 and ‘last_name' is GUINESS1.
When you scroll on the right, you can see it also has a rare condition where ‘actor_id' is = 1.
Similar thing is also there for ‘actor_id' = 3. Let's click on Apply. If you do not understand this
SELECT statement, don't worry about it. We are going to cover this thing in depth in later modules.
Click on Apply and the screen displays Success. Click on Finish. Now you can see the Apply button is disabled.
Once again, go to our Ad hoc query, which we have written a few minutes ago and execute it one more time.
When you executed over here, you can see that line #1 is now changed from PENELOPE and GUINESS to PENELOPE 1
and GUINESS1. Similar thing for line #3, it's also ED2 and CHASE2. We have learned that how successfully
we can edit the row in any table using SQL Editor. On Visual Tab, you can go to any of the cells and double-click
over here. It will make that cell as editable. You can edit the cell and make ED2 to ED and CHASE2 to CHASE.
Now you can see once again there is an Apply button and a Cancel button. Apply is highlighted and if we click on
Apply, the ED and CHASE will be committed and it will be communicated to the database. If you don't like the changes
which we have done, we can easily click on Cancel and you can see they will revert to their original value.
SQL Editor is very powerful. We can also edit it one more way. Click on any line and now go to Edit in the Result Tab.
Click over here and now that particular cell and complete row is editable. The logic of Apply and Cancel remain
the same in all the cases. In this clip, we have learned three different ways to edit any row in SQL Editor.