Now we will see how we can edit SQL Script in SQL Editor. Go to MySQL Workbench home screen.
Click on Edit SQL Script. Let's select SQLAuthority as your Stored Connection and click on Next.
Over here it will ask us ‘Please select SQL file you want to open'. I already created a SQL file, which I'll
select from this Browse menu. I selected the file ‘Test1.sql'. There is an option if I want to execute this file
upon opening. I'll select this one as I know this one is safe to execute. I strongly recommend that don't select
this checkbox if you are not sure about the content of the file, which you are opening. Now click on Finish.
It has executed the SQL, which was part of TEST1.sql. In the TEST1.sql, I had a very simple SELECT statement.
It was SELECT * FROM sakila.actor. It will list us all the actors. Let's write another SELECT over here
and now we will save this file. Let's close TEST1 and now we will open the same file once again.
Go to ‘Open a SQL script file in a new query tab' with a second option in Menu over here and open TEST1 once again.
You can see that TEST1.sql now has two SELECT statements. Let's execute them together.
Select these two statements and click on Execute. Now let's look at our Visual Pane. On Visual Pane, you can see
there are two tabs also over here. One is actor 1 and second one is city 2. One and two is just indicating the
order of the query, how they're executed. They are just an indication. You can reorder them as well.
Actor is now listing all the actors and city is now listing all the cities. Working with SQL Editor is indeed
very easy.