Now we will learn how we can insert a new row using SQL Editor. Go to Schema or database sakila, click on Tables,
right-click on Actors, and select ‘Select Rows'. It has written us rows from table, actor.
Now on the Visual Tab, you can see on the top bar there is a menu. The first menu states ‘Edit current row',
which we have seen it earlier, and now go to the next one. There's a small plus sign on table grid there.
The pop states ‘Insert new row'. Click over here. At the end of the table it has given us a new row.
Here I'll insert a new id, 1000, name is Pinal, last name is Dave, and last updated date, let's put any date.
Now the logical Apply and Cancel is still there. Click on Apply if you want to insert this row.
I'll click on Apply and it has automatically generated INSERT script for us. Now you can see the INSERT script
has been generated. You can see the values when you scroll down the right side. Now click on Apply and
click on Finish. Now you can see Apply and Cancel at this table. If you go to the end of it, you can see
the new row has been inserted. In the next clip, we will see how we can delete the newly inserted row.