In this demonstration, we will download MySQL and install it live. In your browser, go to MySQL.com/downloads.
Over here, you will be able to see various MySQL downloads, MySQL Community Server, MySQL Enterprise Edition,
my MySQL Cluster, MySQL Cluster CGE, MySQL Workbench, GUI Tool, and various other MySQL connectors,
ODBC, .Net, Java platform, Python, C++, C, and PHP. You can download each of these things and install as
they're needed. If you're in a Windows platform, I suggest you download MySQL Installer.
MySQL Installer for Windows contains all of the MySQL products in a single package.
Let's click on Download and it will bring us to the page where we can download MySQL Installer.
MySQL Installer will contain all the MySQL-related products. MySQL Installer provides an easy to use
wizard-based installation experience for all of the MySQL software needs.
You can click over here and download MySQL Installer. In interest of the time, I have already downloaded
MySQL Installer on my local drive. Next, we'll install MySQL using MySQL Installer.