Here you can see I have already downloaded MySQL Installer. Let's double-click it and it brings up Welcome screen.
Now we'll follow a Standard MySQL installation. Click on Install MySQL Products, read and agree to license terms,
click on Next, and it will ask you if you want to check for latest updates. As I've just downloaded my package,
there won't be any update, even though it does not harm to check it one more time.
Let's click on Execute, it will connect to the internet and fetch product update information.
Over here, it gives us various options for setup types. Developer options, it installs all products needed for
MySQL development purposes. This is one which we'll be selecting. However, it's worth noting there are other
options like server only, client only, a full installation, and custom installation. Two more things to note
before we click on Next, first is Installation Path and second is Data Path. Installation Path is where MySQL
will install MySQL and Data Path is where MySQL will install data files. Click on Next.
On the prerequisite screen, it will give us a list of all the prerequisites. In my case, all the prerequisites
are met, hence, we are seeing all green checkmarks. Let's click on Next. Now we'll be installing MySQL and
all the related product. I would like you to pay close attention to the time it takes to install MySQL Server.
The reason is that, after I click on Execute, you'll notice that installing MySQL Server and all the
related product is a very fast and efficient process. Let's click on Execute. (Music)
And we're done. You can see in very few seconds, we installed MySQL Server and all the related products.
Isn't it easy and efficient? Let's click on Next. Here it will ask us to do configuration.
After installation, configuration is a very important task. However, MySQL configuration is very simple to do.
Click on Next. Here, you are to select your server configuration type. We have Development Machine so
we'll leave the Development Machine as a default option. Alternatively, you can also select Server Machine or
Dedicated Machine as well. In the Server Machine, you'll have other applications also running with
MySQL installation; however, in case of the Dedicated Machine, only MySQL product will be running on this machine.
My machine is Development Machine, hence, click Development Machine and click on Next.
Here, you can enable or disable TCP/IP Networking. Let's not change any setting over here and click on Next.
MySQL Server Configuration will ask us to enter Root Password and you can see password strength is medium.
Let me create another admin user over here. I'll give the name Pinal Dave. I left the role ‘DB Admin'.
I'll provide a complex password. Click OK and now we are ready to go to next screen. Click on Next.
On this screen, MySQL will allow us to configure Windows Service Details. Here, we will change the
Windows Service Name so we can easily identify our MySQL installation. We will give it the name as SQLAuthority.
Now click on Next. Here you can see now Server Configuration is complete. We can click Next one more time and
Samples and Examples will be configured. Click on Next and now, along with MySQL Server Samples and Examples,
we are ready to go. Click on Next. On the very next screen it will ask us if you want to start MySQL Workbench
after Setup, yes or no. I'll leave this one on because that's the next thing which we are going to discuss.
Click Finish and immediately you can see MySQL Workbench is open.