Now let's see a quick example how MySQL Workbench works. MySQL Workbench has three major workspaces --
SQL Development, Data Modeling, and Server Administration. In the SQL Development, we can run queries and
modify data; in SQL Modeling, we can create and manage models; and in Server Administration Area, we can do
various server-related operations like restarting a server or making a backup. Now let's see a quick example how
we can use SQL Development Area. Double-click on our server name, which we have just created
and it will open SQL Editor. SQL Editor is the area where we will write query to retrieve data, as well as
modify data. In this very first initial example, we'll just retrieve few data. On the left side, there's
Object Explorer and right below it there's an Information area. We can see there are three schemas over here.
Let's expand World schema. When we expand World schema, we can see Tables, Views, and Routines.
Let's further expand Tables. Upon expanding Tables, we can see the name of the Tables - City, Country, and
Country Language. Let's click on City. Upon clicking on the City, in the Information area we can see the
definition of the Table City. City has five columns and ID column is an integer in primary key.
Let's expand City Table as well. Upon expanding City Table, we can see four object groups -- Columns, Indexes,
Foreign Keys, and Triggers. Let's expand Columns. Here, we can see the same five columns once again.
Click on ID and in Information area you can see the definition of ID. Now let's select data from City.
Right-click over City and select very first option about Selecting Rows. This option automatically brought
a simple query for SELECT * FROM world.city and this result is displayed in the Result tab.
This Result tab is also very powerful. You can select any row and get ‘Edit' from the menu over here or
‘Insert new row', as well as ‘Delete any row'. Let's try to delete 5th row.
Select 5th row, click on ‘Delete selected row'. You can see between 4 and 6 there is no row. The row #5 is deleted.
Well, that's enough for SQL Editor. You will learn about SQL Editor in depth in a later module.
Now very quickly, we'll see a simple example how we can use Server Administration Area.
Double-click on our connection and it will open Server Administration Area.
Server Administration Area will display as Server Status. Here is the information about our server.
Our server is currently running. You can also see system information, CPU and Memory.
Additionally, there are various vital server information like Connection Usage, Traffic, Query Cache, and
Key Efficiency are also displayed over here. You can use the same area to startup and shut down my SQL Server as well.
There are various Connection Parameters, System Information, Server Logs, and a lot of other Administrative Tasks
available in this area. We will explore each of them in a dedicated module. Let's close this one
and now we are back into MySQL Workbench main screen.