Now let's see a simple example how we'll use MySQL Command Line Client when we don't have access to
MySQL Workbench. When you open MySQL Command Line Client, the very first thing it will ask is Password.
Enter your password, hit Enter, and it will bring you to a command prompt. If you want further help over here,
you can type ‘help;' and it will give you pretty much every single help available for this command prompt.
Now let's try to see what are the different databases installed on this server.
For that, we will be using a command called show. Type ‘show databases' and click on Enter.
It will list all the databases which we have. Let's use the word ‘database'. Type ‘use world' and hit Enter.
You can see the message displayed ‘Database changed'. Now let's try to see, what are the different tables
world database has. You'll use, once again, show command, show ‘show tables;'. Let's hit Enter and it will list
every single table that belongs to this database. If you remember in MySQL Workbench, we retrieved a few data
from City Table. Let's try to do the same over here. Let's retrieve 10 rows from City Tables.
So type ‘SELECT * FROM City LIMIT 10' and hit Enter and it will display you top 10 rows from City Table.
When you don't have access to the MySQL Workbench, you can quickly use this as a replacement.