We will be using SQL to access MySQL Database. At that time, the system is often called Client/Server System.
Let's understand Client/Server System. There are three important components for any Client/Server System.
Clients: Clients are like PCs, Macs, laptops, tablets, smartphones, etc.
Server: Server usually stores files. When Server stores database along with files, it is called Database Server.
MySQL is Database Server application.
Networks: Networks are communication links between Client and Server. Beside including lines and cables,
Network also includes hubs, router, and other interface components. In many enterprises, large database files
are also stored on a network storage. Networking components connect server with network storage.
In simple topology, client and server are both on a same network. They are often known as land or local area network.
If there are more than two lands located in a separate geographic location, that's called WAN, which is
wide area network. If we assume there is a database on this Client/Server System, we can say that client sends
a request in terms of the SQL query to the server. Server, in turn, passes the same SQL query to the database
and database query returns the results back to the client and then the client, which can be PC, Mac,
audio handheld devices, will display the result.