Now we will try to understand how Web Application Server works with database with real life example.
Let's assume you want to check your email. You take your computer, open it, start it, and run your web browser.
In the web browser, you will type your URL address. As soon as you type your URL address, web browser will now
send the request. The request will go to internet by your ISP. ISP stands for Internet Service Provider.
Once your request goes to internet, Group Domain Server will now forward that request to Application Server.
This Application Server is where your email application is hosted. Application Server will process all the HTML
and dynamic pages. The front end of any application is pretty much the same across every single user while using
this application. For example, if you are using Gmail, Yahoo or Hotmail, the look and feel will be pretty much
the same across every single user of Gmail, Yahoo or Hotmail. However, their emails will be different,
the data will be different. You will have data from your friend and other users will have data from their
friends and relatives. Data will differ, but the page will look the same. That's exactly what will happen in
Application Server. It will pass the static HTML's and will pass back the dynamic pages through the
Application Server. However, every request for data will now go to Database Server.
Database Server will have DBMS or Database Management System. Management System will query user data and
will give it back to Database Server. Database Server will later pass back the data to Application Server,
along with HTML and dynamic page will be returned to internet and at the end will go to web browser of user.
It's hard to imagine that there will be any application without any kind of database on the back end.
As of 2008, MySQL is the most popular Database Management System on planet earth.