We noticed that Database Management System plays a very important role in any application.
There are two kinds of database models -- Relational Database Model and Non-Relational Database Model.
MySQL is a Relational Database Model. Let's quickly see a couple of history bites before we move to
understanding relational database management system concept in depth.
In 1970, Dr. E.F. Code has developed the concepts of relational database.
Any relational database will help following three most important properties.
There will be less redundancy between the data, retrieval of the data will be very efficient, and
the data modification should be intuitive. Though relational database can get complex, the basic three
properties of less redundancy, efficient data retrieval, and intuitive data modification usually stays the same
because relational database concepts enforces them. Let's see what are the relational database concepts in depth.