For any relational database model, there are four very important concepts. A model for relational database states
the data is storing one or more tables. It also states that each table is two-dimensional.
Each dimensions are columns and rows. Intersection of the columns and rows are cells.
Let's see them a little bit more in detail. A table: Any relational database consists of one or more tables.
Tables are usually modeled after real world entities. For example, an address table would have
Address 1, Address 2, City, State, Country, and Zip code or Postal Code. It's quite possible on a single
address, one or many different persons are staying. It's quite possible that there is nobody staying at
the address as well. Address can have different types, like Work, Home, Factory or Open Ground.
Well, all of them can be tables. A column: A column represents some attribute of the entity of the table.
For example, in the case of the address, as we discussed, it can be Street #, Apartment #, Address 1,
City, Zip code or any other detail. Columns are also known as fields. A row usually contains a set of values
for a single instance of entity. For example, in address table it will have a single address.
A single address may contain multiple columns. An address can be Apartment #, followed by Street #, followed by City,
State, and Zip code. If the table has multiple Countries data, then there may be an additional column for Country
and the row will contain Name of the Country. Well, this discussion leads to our last discussion about cells.
Cells are nothing but intersection of row and column. One cell may contain Apartment # and another cell may
contain Street #. They can belong to different columns and they can belong to different rows.
It is just an intersection and each of the cells will have a single value. Well, think about it this way.
Apartment # may be a number, but street name may not be a #, but may be a string. Now we are leading to another
concept that cell can have different kinds of value. It can be a number or it can be a string or
it's quite possible it's a mix of both of them. In relational database, everything into the table has a
relation to each other, as well as there is a relation among the tables. Well let's see that in the next clip.