The most important part of any relational database model is relations. In relational database, there are always
relations between various tables, as well as columns of different tables. They are associated with each other
with Primary Key, as well as Foreign Key. Primary Key: Primary Key uniquely identifies each row of the table.
There can't be more than one Primary Key per table. The most important property for Primary Key is that it
cannot allow any NULL. It's not necessarily that Primary Key has only one column, there can be more than column
for Primary Key as well. When there are more than one column builds of Primary Key, they are called composite columns.
Let's try to understand what can be a good candidate for Primary Key. Let's assume that you have a table called Student.
In a table Student, Student ID will be a good candidate for Primary Key. If you have a table called Supplier,
in that case, you can also go with Supply Name as a Primary Key as well. In your system, you don't want
two suppliers with the same name; however, you have any reason you have two supplied with same name and
your system requirement is to allow that, you might have to add another column, which we call Supplier ID.
Instead of identifying each row with Supplier Name, now you have identified each row with Supplier ID.
Now think of it, what could be the reason that you have a same name for two different suppliers?
It's quite possible both of them are supplying different things; one is supplying pencils and another one is
supplying erasers. In that case, you have two options. Either you add Supplier ID, which I would prefer or
you can create a composite column as a Primary Key. You can use Supplier Name and Supplier Item as a composite
Primary Key. Personally, I would add Supplier ID. The same Primary Key will be also another column in another
table where we will have Foreign Key relationship. A narrow Primary Key translates to less random data and
eventually leads to higher performance. Well, we'll talk about this thing with an example in our advanced course,
but for a moment let's assume that you have created Supplier ID as a Primary Key; however, you still want every
supplier's name unique in the system. What should be the workaround for that? Well, the workaround is to create
Unique Key or Supplier Name. Unique Key is not a Primary Key; however, it still ensures the data is not duplicated.
You can have multiple Unique Keys in one table. Unique Key also allows one NULL, whereas Primary Key does
not allow any NULL. We talked about Foreign Key a little bit earlier. Foreign Key: Foreign Keys are the columns
in a table that refers to Primary Key of another table. Let's assume that we have a table called Purchase Order.
In the Purchase Order table, we will have Supplier ID. Supplier ID will have a Foreign Key relationship with the
Primary Key of Supplier table. The primary responsibility of Foreign Key is to enforce referential integrity
throughout the database. There can be different kinds of relationships between Primary Key and Foreign Key.
There can be one-to-one, one-to-many or many-to-many relationship.
Let's understand one-to-one relationship. Here, we have Person and Address. One person has one address and
one address has one person. This is a one-to-one relationship. However, it can go complex.
One person might have multiple addresses. He might have billing address and mailing address, as well as his
office address. Now, a person has multiple addresses, that is a one-to-many relationship.
Let's look at the same example a little differently, one-to-many again. This time, there is one address and
there are multiple persons staying at that one address. Isn't that the case in our home too?
We have multiple people staying at one single address. Let's go a little bit more real, many-to-many.
Some might have a one-to-one relationship with one address and it's quite possible that certain place,
one address might have multiple people staying there, and it's also possible that all three of them working
at the same place. This is a great example of many-to-many relationship. Here, the office address has a
three-relationship, whereas one home address has a one-relationship, and another home has a two-relationship.
The primary task of relational database is to retrieve data efficiently from this various relationship and have
less redundant data stored in database.