Column definition is very important. We create Primary Key, Unique Key, Foreign Key, and Indexes on column.
Column definition is very critical when we talk about performance. In column definition, data type determines
the type of information we store in column. For example, we have various kinds of data types -- string, integer,
float, date and time. We can store any character string in CHAR or VARCHAR data type and then store any
numeric value in integer data type. If you have decimal value, we can put them in a float and if we have date
data type, for example, birthday or anniversary date or joining date, we can use date and time date data type.
Along with data type, there are a few important properties of column definition as well. Let's look at them.
Default Value. We can specify a default value for any column. Let's see a scenario where you have a requirement
to log current date/time of data inserted into a table. You can create a column with the name ‘insert a date'
and by default give it a value of ‘current date/time'. What it means is that every single time any data, which is
inserted into that table, the column ‘insert a date' will be automatically populated with default value,
but not every column qualifies for default value. There are cases where you may not know what to put in a column.
At that time, you can leave the column as NULL. This is called NULLable column. Now, you can have a default value
in the column or you can just leave the column NULL and there won't be any data there.
You can later go and update either this default value or NULL value.
Auto increment column: Auto increment column is a column which is continuously increasing by the interval,
which we specified in the column definition. Auto increment column is very important because in many cases
it is difficult to identify column qualifying for Primary Key. In that case, we can add an auto increment column.
Now, auto increment column will not have a NULL value. Additionally, it will be always incrementing distinct value.
This is a good candidate for Primary Key. Personally, I believe defining column data types and column properties
is one of the most essential tasks for any database designer. With this, we complete understanding of our last
concept in Fundamentals of Database Design.