Let's open MySQL Workbench and SQL Editor and now we will see a few of the examples of how INSERT works.
We'll start with creating a sample table and we'll be inserting all the data into this sample table.
This is how we make sure that we do not upset live data. We'll be using Database sakila. We'll create a table,
which is ActorSample. It has actor_id, first_name, last_name, and last_update. Actor_id is small integer and
it's unsigned; however, it's NOT NULL and it's AUTO_INCREMENTING. As we are not specifying any other properties
of AUTO_INCREMENT, it will start with 1 and will increment the value of the column by 1 as well.
The first_name is varchar and it's NOT NULL, last_name is NULL, and last_update is timestamp data type and it's
also NOT NULL; however, there is an important property defined here, which is DEFAULT. The default value of this
column is CURRENT_TIMESTAMP. What it means is that if you do not specify any value to be inserted for last_update
column, it will be automatically populated by CURRENT_TIMESTAMP. Let's start with our very first example of INSERT.
Let's execute this one and you can see in Output, it has already created a table for us.
Now we'll start with a very simple example where we will insert a single row into the table.
The script is ‘INSERT INTO table name sakila.actorsample'. Here, specified here three of our column --
those are first_name, last_name, and last_update. Please note that we are not specifying here column actor_id.
The reason of that is very simple. It's going to be AUTO_INCREMENT. What it means is that we do not have to
explicitly enter data into this column. As and when we insert data, this will be auto-populated by AUTO_INCREMENT
property of a column. Let's see example of that as well. We are going to use VALUE clause right after the
INSERT Statement. In the VALUE clause, we are going to specify the property, first_name I'm specifying Pinal,
last_name as Dave, and last_update as any date. Let's select this one and click on Execute.
You can see in OUTPUT clause, the message is ‘1 row affected'. Now let's check the data into this table.
Select ‘SELECT * FROM' table and click on Execute. You can see that has inserted one row, which is actor_id 1 because
it's the first value, first_name Pinal, last_name Dave, and last_update date, which we have just specified.
As in our INSERT, we did not specify any of the time component, it has by default assumed time component of 00-00.
Now let's go to second script. Here is the second script. Let's compare this one with the first one.
You can see there are two major differences. First is there are no column lists in the second script and
the second is default specified over here. Let's first execute this one and we'll talk about that afterwards.
Click on Execute and now check the data. We have successfully inserted the second row and it states Nupur Dave
in the date. If you notice, it's the same data which we have just inserted; however, in earlier one, we did not
specify actor_id because actor_id was auto-populated. However, when we are inserting data into table and
not specifying the list of the column, at that time we will have to specify every single column's value in the
value list, as well as it has to be in the same order as the original table. What it means is that this default
stands for actor_id, Nupur for first_name and Dave for last_name, as well as the date, which we have specified
is for the fourth column. Column order has to match to the original order. If I change the order of Dave in the
date, it's not going to insert the data properly and it may give us Error. If we do not specify default,
MySQL will also give an Error. When we specify the default, it will go and take the default value for this column.
In this case, the default value will be AUTO_INCREMENTED and AUTO-INCREMENT will be adding 1 to the original value
as we have not specified any other AUTO_INCREMENT data. That means we will have value 2 over here.
Well, let's continue with our next example. In this example, you can see that now we have only two columns
where we are inserting data -- one is first_name and second one is last_name -- and the data, which we are inserting,
is Pinal Dave. Let's think for a moment what would happen in this case. In case of the first_name, the value
Pinal will go; in case of the last_name, the value Dave will go. What will be the value of last_update?
Let's go and check the value in our table definition. In table definition, we have specified the last value is
of data type timestamp and will have a default value of CURRENT_TIMESTAMP. What it means is that if you do not
specify the last_update, it will automatically take the current date/time of the Server where MySQL is installed.
Let's exhibit this and relate it to our assumption. Select the statement, click on Execute, and now select
the data from table. You can see over here that third record is inserted with first_name Pinal, last_name Dave,
and the date is current date/time from my system. Now, let's go to next script and understand that.
In our next script, we have only one column specified in our INSERT Statement and the value is Pinal.
There is no value for last_name, as well as last_update and actor_id. Let's try to guess what will be the value
in each of these columns? Well, in case of the actor_id, once again we will have AUTO_INCREMENT value and
we will see 4. In case of the last_update, as we have noticed, we will have the current date/time of Server,
but what will be the value of the last_name. Let's go to our column definition one more time and see what it will be.
You can see last_name column is defined as NULL. What it means is that if you pass any value to this column,
it will take that value, but if you do not pass any value to this column, it will just take that as a NULL.
Well, let's execute this and validate that. Select the statement and click on Execute. As we have expected,
actor_id is 4, first_name is Pinal, last_update is current date/time of the Server, but the value of the
last_name column is NULL. Isn't this interesting? That sometimes we feel that we are to specify every single
column, but as we start narrowing down, we learn that there are so many things, which are dependent on the
definition of table, which we have defined earlier. That is why Data Modeling is considered as one of the most
challenging tasks. Now, let's try to do the same thing with last_name Dave. Here, we have not specified the
first_name, but we are only specifying the last_name. What do you think will happen? Let's go all the way up and
see here the first_name only states it's NOT NULL. There is no default value specified. What is means is that
this column has to have a value. If we do not specify what to be inserted into this column, MySQL will not let
the entire row to be inserted into this table. Let's see that into action. Now we select the statement and click
on Execute and on the bottom over here, you can see that there is an Error. Error states first row does not have
a default value. What it means is that if you do not have a default value, you will have to insert some data in it.
You cannot just walk away without specifying any value for the column, which is marked as NOT NULL and does not
have a default. Well, let's see one more example. Insert into table name, column's first_name, last_name,
and last_update. The value Pinal will go into first_name and NULL will go into last_name and default value will
go into last_update. What will happen over here is that we will see in the first_name column value Pinal,
in last_name NULL, and last_update current date/time of the system. Let's select the statement and execute it.
Now, we'll go and check the data into the table. You can see actor_id 5 is over here and first_name is Pinal,
last_name is NULL, our Server's default date/time is in last_update column. Now, let's go a little bit more
advanced and see how we can insert multiple rows. So, here is the example where we will see how we can set
multiple values into table. The first method is very simple and very easy to increment. We have INSERT INTO table name
and column name listed over here. In VALUE clause, we have first column and comma and second column and a comma
and we have third column. We can have more than three columns over here as well. With this kind of syntax,
we do not have to specify INSERT Statement again and again. Let's execute this one and now select the data.
Scroll down and you can see now we have three records inserted, which is Pinal Dave with date 17, Nupur Dave with
date 18, Shaivi Dave with date 19. There is one more method where we can use SELECT statement to insert data.
For example, if you want to insert all the data where the actor's first_name is Nick into this table,
we can use this kind of syntax. Let's see the SELECT statement first. There you can see we have three names with
actor's first_name is Nick. Now, we will just write INSERT statement just on the top of this SELECT statement.
In INSERT, we have three columns -- first_name, last_name, and last_updated. In case of the SELECT statement,
let's select everything and click on Execute. When we execute, we can see there are three rows, which are returned.
Let's go and check the data. SELECT * FROM ActorSample and click on Select. Let's scroll down all the way to
the bottom and you can see that there are three new records, which are inserted, which is NICK WAHLBERG,
NICK STALLONE, and NICK DEGENERES. Well, you can see how easy it is to insert data into table by using
SELECT statement. Let's clean up and drop this table. Now, in the next clip we will learn about UPDATE statement.