Now, let's see UPDATE statement into action. We'll be using sakila database and we'll be creating our
custom table. We want to make sure the table, which we use, does not modify any of the live or production system.
The table, which we are going to create, is almost the same table which we have created in our INSERT script.
Click on Create Table script and click on Execute. This script is very similar to the script, which we have
used in our INSERT statement demonstrations. Click on Execute and now, new table, which is sakila.actorsample,
is populated with the same data of sakila.actor. First, we will learn about Update Single Row Using Single Column.
Here is the UPDATE statement where we are updating sakila.actorsample. SET keyword has first_name.
Every single row in the first column will be now populated with Pinal. What we want to do is that we only want
to update the value of the first record where ‘actor_id = 1'. Now we are limiting our update to only one column
and one row and now, before we check our data, we'll do the same operation with the last_name as well.
What it means is that we'll now update the last_name column to value Dave where actor_id is also 1.
Let's select this one and click on Execute. Now let's go back and check our data. The value of the first_name is
Pinal and the value of the last_name is Dave. Now, let's move further. In an earlier example, we have updated
first_name and last_name separately. We do not have to do that. We can update first_name and last_name of
single row or together. For example, over here, I'm going to update the row where ‘actor_id = 2' with first_name
Pinal and last_name Dave. Please note, the current value are NICK and WAHLBERG. Now, let's execute this script
and do select on the table. You can see the OR value is now replaced with Pinal and Dave. This time, we did not
have to write two separate UPDATE statements to update a single row. We can update a single row with multiple
columns by specifying all the columns into SET clause. Let's take this one into next level.
Carefully observe the WHERE clause. WHERE clause has actor_id and list of the actor_id. What it means is that
every actor_id with value 3, 4 or 5 will be now updated with the value Pinal. Let's execute this and check our data.
Upon checking our data, we can see this change also happened over here. Well, what we did is that we specified
a list and multiple rows were updated for a single column. We can take it to the further next level where we
update multiple columns and multiple rows. Here is the example. Here, we have WHERE condition where actor_id in
6, 7 or 8, which means these are the three rows which we are discussing over here. We are updating first_name
with Pinal, last_name with Dave, and last_update with DEFAULT value. DEFAULT value will populate current
date/time of the Server in the column. Let's select this one and click on Execute and now, check the data.
In resultset, we can clearly see that 6, 7, and 8 row has now Pinal Dave value everywhere and last_update date
is updated to current date/time. Let's see one more concept. Here is the concept of using subqueries.
We have UPDATE statement where we are updating sakila.actorsample and setting value first_name to Nupur and
WHERE condition has actor_id. However, let's pay additional attention to the WHERE clause.
Here, we have subquery in our WHERE clause. Let's execute the subquery independently and you can see the
subquery is returning its value of 1, 10, 20, 40, 50, and so onwards. These are the lists of actor_id who
all work in the ‘film_id = 1'. What it means is that all these actors work in a single film, which has ‘film_id = 1'.
Now we will change the first_name of every single actor who has acted in the film 1 to Nupur. Let's execute this one.
Well, Execute did not happen successfully and we can see that in Error. Error Code 1175: You are using safe
update mode and you tried to update a table without WHERE clause. Now, we are definitely using a WHERE clause;
however, by default, MySQL Workbench works into safe mode. Let's change that. Let's go to Edit and go to
Preference, go to SQL Queries, and here uncheck Safe Update. Additionally, it also requires us to do reconnection.
I unchecked this option and click on OK. Now click on this icon, which suggests reconnect to DBMS.
Now, once again, try to run this query. This time, query is ran successfully and it has updated 10 rows.
Let's go to our table and check the data in it. We can see the very first row is now updated to Nupur because
‘actor_id = 1' was also actor in a ‘film_id = 1'. Scrolling down, we can see another value where actor_id is 10.
Now you can see how easy it is to update single and multiple rows in MySQL. We can use complex logic in the
WHERE clause, as well as subquery to update our data. Let's do cleanup and drop our table.
Next, we'll see another important concept of Delete.