Here, we are in MySQL Workbench in the SQL Editor and we'll see an example of DELETE statement.
We'll be using sakila database and now we'll create very similar table, which we have created in earlier examples.
Table is ActorSample and has four columns -- actor_id, first_name, last_name, and last_update. Click on Execute
and table is successfully created. Now we will populate the table with sakila.actor table.
We'll be using INSERT statement. Insert into sakila.actorsample column names and we'll be retrieving the same
column from sakila.actor table. Let's execute this one and now we have our sample table ready, which we will use
to exercise our DELETE statement. Let's see our very first example. Here, we are going to delete a single row.
First, let's select our data. You will see in our data that our first row is actor_id 1 and first_name is Pinal
and last_name is Dave. Let's execute this statement where we have ‘DELETE FROM table name WHERE actor_id = 1'.
If you look at this statement, the structure from FROM is very similar to SELECT, as well as UPDATE.
Click on Execute and now, once again, check your data. We can see that in data, the actor_id 1 row is now deleted.
Well, let's go further down and this time, try to delete multiple rows together. We are going to use a list in
WHERE clause ‘WHERE actor_id IN (3,4,5)'. Let's select this entire statement and click on Execute.
Upon selecting the data, we can see that we no more have row 3, 4, and 5. This is how you can use WHERE clause
in a SELECT statement to delete one or multiple rows. However, just like UPDATE statement, you can be creating
with subquery in DELETE statement as well. Here, we have a subquery where we are selecting all the actor_id
who work in the ‘film_id = 1'. Select the statement and click on Select. You can see various actor_id over here,
actor_id 10, 20, and 30 - let's remember them for a moment and our DELETE statement states
‘DELETE FROM table name WHERE actor_id' into this all actor_id's. Let's select the entire statement and click
on Execute. Upon checking the data in the table, we can see that now we do not have record id 10, 20 or 30 over here.
They all got deleted because we executed this DELETE statement. You can observe the DELETE statement is extremely
easy to do. Just missing a WHERE condition is capable to delete an entire table as well. Let's see that in our
next example. Here, we do not have any WHERE clause. What it means is that, now, entire table sakila.actorsample
will be deleted. Select the statement and click on Execute. If you are paying attention to our Output Window,
you can see that it displays 187 rows affected. Actually, they're all deleted.
Now, let's go to ‘SELECT * FROM ActorSample'. Click on Execute and we are getting no rows over here.
The reason was that we did not use the WHERE clause and that's why every single record from this table has been deleted.
Well, with this we complete our demonstration for Data Modification. Let's clean up by executing this statement.
And now we will see Summary in Sixty Seconds.